Speaker 1: Senator Brown and Senator Bennett for championing this issue for not this Congress, but for years.
Before I came
Speaker 1: to
Speaker 2: Washington, these
two men were
Speaker 2: standing up and talking about
the moral core of
Speaker 2: our country. If
Speaker 3: you want to see how a nation
is doing,
Don't look at
Speaker 3: the buildings we build, how many billionaires we have, just look at children.
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): And what is galling me right now
is that we
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): have come to the one yard line, we are at an inflection point in our
country where we
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): have to ask the question, who
are we?
My friend,
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): Senator Bennett, and
Speaker 5: I have been working with kids well before we came here, and he rattled off data that should be
repeated.
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): I say this is a moral issue, but he has shown this is an economic issue. We are the wealthiest nation on the planet Earth,
Woman 7: and of the top 41 countries,
We're
Woman 7: at 38 and poor kids. And
what he
Woman 7: pointed out is that poverty costs all of us. It is a deep, self-inflicted wound in this society
Woman 8: because poverty costs this nation over a trillion dollars as measured by economists. But I'm telling you right now, economists don't measure all the things that are important. Our GDP.
Woman 8: does not reflect well-being. It doesn't reflect how many antidepressants people take or how many child deaths there are. But the truth of our economy is every dollar we invest in getting children out of poverty returns $8 to this
Speaker 9: economy. So
it is an economic
Speaker 9: issue, clearly.
Woman 8: Clearly.
It is a
Woman 8: globally competitive issue because the nation in a global knowledge-based society, the nation whose children learn the most will earn the most
and will out-compete. It is a
Speaker 9: national security issue as we go up against countries like China, whose top 10% of
Speaker 10: their graduating high school classes
Speaker 10: Outnumber all the children we have virtually. But
it is a moral issue,
Speaker 11: most of all. If we are going to create a more beloved community, how do we treat our children? Children
who live in
Speaker 11: poverty literally
have
Woman 7: physical effects. Poverty is...
Woman 7: is violence.
Study after
Speaker 12 (higher-pitched voice): study shows that the brain development of children in poverty is inhibited. Literally, the stress hormones, the cortisol, it is akin to an adult having a traffic accident every single day. It is an indicator of childhood
trauma.
Poverty
Speaker 12 (higher-pitched voice): is a moral obscenity,
and we, the
Speaker 12 (higher-pitched voice): richest nation on the planet, that year after year are rich are getting richer, our children are getting poorer. Who are we when
we pledge allegiance to a
Speaker 12 (higher-pitched voice): flag and say liberty and justice for all? Who
are we?
We don't even know
Speaker 12 (higher-pitched voice): the demographic changes in our country. We have cities across America where one out of every 10 child is being raised by a grandparent.
And so here
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): we're discussing childhood poverty, and some people are talking about work requirements when we know from the data from conservative think tanks,
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): to what we see in other nations like Canada, that things like the child allowance, or in our country, the child tax credit, increase workforce participation. But if you get rid of the child tax credit, those grandparents raising grandchildren, half of them plunge
Speaker 13: back
into poverty.
and the
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): stories are profound. You heard from my colleague in Colorado. We know families in New Jersey, like a woman I just saw named Margarita. She used her child tax credit payments for exactly what so many said they would be used for. She used them for food
for her children, for school
Speaker 14: supplies to keep the electricity running in her house.
We've heard
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): stories that they're used for a car bill to get people to work. They're used to pay for childcare that they need for their family so that they can work. Families are not using this money so they can quit their jobs. Quite the contrary, they're using them so they can get to work. Mr. President, we
are a
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): nation in crisis because of how we treat our children.
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): The child tax credit is a lifeline
for
Speaker 15: the millions of grandparents raising grandchildren. It's a lifeline for low-income
children.
Speaker 13: And
Speaker 16: so, you heard it from Senator Bennett. We are at an inflection point. What will we do right now? Will
we...
Extend
Speaker 16: the child tax credit? Will we make the full
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): refundability permanent? Will we keep people having these monthly checks? That is the policy question, but the question before us really is a moral one.
For once and for
Speaker 15: all, this is not partisan.
It's a
Speaker 1: defining moment for the character of our country. And I say, words are not enough. We should show with the child tax credit
the
Speaker 1: truth in our policies, what we do with our budgets. We should show our love through what we do, not what we say.
And the best
Speaker 16: leading indicator of that will always be how the most vulnerable in our society are doing, how we take care of our
Speaker 17: elderly, and in this case, how we care for our children. I'm honored to now have come to the floor our senator from Georgia,
I
Speaker 17: would mark as much as I love the senator from Ohio and the senator from Colorado The
Senate for
Speaker 18: Georgia has a much better haircut. I yield the floor
Senator from
Speaker 19: Ohio